[GENTLE ORCHESTRAL MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: All right,
this is CS50's Introduction
to Programming with Python.
My name is David Malan and this is
our week on functions and variables.
But odds are, many of you, most of you,
have never actually programmed before.
So let's start by doing just that.
Let me go ahead here
and open up my computer
and on it, a program called
Visual Studio Code or VS
Code, which is just a very
popular program nowadays
for actually writing code.
Now, you don't have to write
code using this particular tool.
In fact, all we need
at the end of the day
is a so-called text editor,
a program for writing text.
And, heck, if you really want,
you could even use something
like Google Docs or Microsoft Word.
You'd have to save it
in the right format,
but really, at the end of the day, all
you need is a program for writing text
because that's what code is-- text.
Now within this particular
program, I'm going
to have the ability to
create one or more files
via this top portion of the screen.
And I'm going to do
so by diving right in
and doing this at the
bottom of my screen.
At the bottom of my screen is
a so-called terminal window
and this is a command line interface
or CLI interface to the underlying
computer, be it your Mac or your PC
or even some server in the cloud.
And what I'm going to do here is
literally write, "code" and then
the name of the file that I want
to code, for instance, Hello.py.
As we'll soon see, any program that you
write in Python generally has a file
name that ends in .py to indicate to
the computer that it's indeed a program
written in Python.
Now you'll see here at the top of
my screen, I have a blinking cursor,
a line one-- which is where the very
first line of my code is going to go--
and then just a tab that reminds me
of the name of this file Hello.py.
And without even
knowing much Python, I'm
going to write my very first
program here as follows--
print("hello,world").
And you'll see that, at my
keyboard, some of my thoughts
were finished for me.
I only had to type one parenthesis and
the other one automatically appeared,
and that's just the feature that we'll
see of tools like this tool here.
Now even if you've
never programmed before,
odds are you can guess, infer what
this simple program is going to do.
And it's only one line.
print("hello,world").
Indeed, when I run this
program ultimately,
it's just going to say,
Hello to the world.
And, in fact, this is a very famous--
perhaps the most
canonical-- program that you
can write as your very first program
in Python or any other language,
and so that's what I've done here.
But on my Mac, my PC, even my
phone, I'm generally in the habit,
like you, of running programs
by double clicking an icon
or just tapping on the screen.
But I see no such icons here.
And in fact, that's because my
interface to at least my current Mac
or PC or some server in the
cloud, is again only a CLI--
command line interface--
which even though it
might feel like it's a step back
from the menus and buttons and icons
that you and I take for granted
every day, you'll find, we think,
that it's ultimately a much more
powerful interface and incredibly
popular to use among
programmers in the real world.
So to run this program, I'm
going to have to use a command
and I'm going to move my cursor back
down to the bottom of the screen
here where previously I
already ran one command--
the command Code which has the effect
of opening VS Code in my computer,
and then I passed in the name of
the file that I wanted to code up.
Now I have a chance to
type a second command,
and you'll see I see
a second dollar sign.
Now the dollar sign here doesn't
indicate any kind of currency or money,
it just is the symbol
that's generally used
to indicate your prompt-- where
the command line interface wants
you to put those commands.
Now the command I can run
here is going to be this--
I'm going to run Python of Hello.py.
Now why is that?
Well, it turns out that when I actually
write code in a language like Python,
it's of course stored in that file--
Hello.py, but I need to
interpret the code top to bottom,
left to right so that the
computer knows what to do.
Indeed, at the end of the
day, even if you don't really
know much about
computers, you've probably
heard the computers only understand
zeros and ones, the so-called binary
system.
Well if that's the case, then something
that says "print" and parentheses
and quote unquote hello world,
is not surely zeros and ones.
We have to somehow translate
it into the zeros and ones
that the computer understands.
Now fortunately, so long as you've
installed such a program in advance,
there's a program as well
as a language called Python.
So Python is not only a language
in which we're going to write code,
it's also a program otherwise
known as an interpreter
that you install for free on your own
Mac or PC or some server in the cloud
and you can then run that program, that
interpreter, passing to it as input
the name of your file
like mine here, Hello.py.
And then that program,
that interpreter, will
handle the process of reading
it top to bottom, left to right
and translating it effectively
into those zeros and ones
that the computer can understand.
So let's do just that.
Let me go back to VS Code here.
I already typed out Python of
Hello.py but I didn't get hit Enter.
And that's what's now going
to kick off this command
and hopefully, if I didn't
mess any of this up,
I should see my very first
program's output to the screen.
And voila, hello, world.
So if you too have typed
exactly that same code
and have executed exactly
that same command,
you will have written your very
first program in this case in Python.
Well now let's take a
step back and consider,
what is it that we
actually just did and what
is it we're looking here on the screen?
Well first and foremost, in
most any programming language,
you tend to have access to
what are called functions.
A function is like an
action or a verb that
lets you do something in the program.
And generally speaking, any language
comes with some predetermined set
of functions-- some very basic actions
or verbs that the computer will already
know how to do for you,
that the language, really,
will know how to do for you.
And you, the programmer, the human,
can use those functions at will
to get the computer to do those things.
Now the program in question here,
Hello.py is using one function.
And you could perhaps guess what it is.
That function is, of course,
going to be this function print
and that print function,
of course, doesn't
print some preordained string of text.
That is to say, it prints whatever
it is you want it to print.
And here too, do we have another
piece of terminology in the world
of programming, namely arguments.
An argument is an input to a function
that somehow influences its behavior.
The people who invented
Python, of course,
didn't necessarily know
what it is you and I
are going to want to print to the
screen, so they designed this print
function using these
parentheses with the ability
to take as input some
string of text, be it
in English or any other
human language, that is
what you want this function
ultimately to print onto the screen.
And what is it that the program
is ultimately doing on the screen?
Well, it's printing, of course.
It's showing us hello,
world on the screen.
And that's generally in
programming known as a side effect.
It can be visual, it can be audio.
In this case, it's something
that appears on the screen
and functions, therefore, can
indeed have these side effects.
One of the things they can
do as this verb or action is
to display on the screen as a side
effect, something like those words
that we wanted--
hello, world.
So that's my first program and,
you know, I'm feeling pretty good.
Everything worked as planned.
I didn't make any
mistakes, but, honestly,
when you're learning
how to program and even
once you've learned how to program years
later, you're going to make mistakes.
And those mistakes, of
course, are referred
to a term you might already
know, which is that of a bug.
A bug is a mistake in a program
and they can take so many forms.
And take comfort, perhaps, in
knowing that over the coming weeks,
you're going to make so many mistakes.
You're going to have so many bugs
in your code, just like I did
and just as I still do.
And those bugs themselves
are just mistakes
that are problems for you to solve.
And over the weeks to come,
we're going to give you
a lot of tools both mental and technical
via which you can solve those problems.
But just don't get discouraged if when
writing your program for the first time
it doesn't even work that first time,
it will with time, with practice,
and with experience.
So let me deliberately
now make a mistake
that there was a non-zero chance I
might have done accidentally already,
but I got lucky.
Let me go ahead and
just suppose I forgot
to include something like
the closing parenthesis
at the end of this line of code.
The code is almost correct,
it's like 99% of the way there,
but now that I've pointed
it out, it's pretty obvious
that it's missing that
closed parenthesis.
But even little, seemingly minor details
like that, that you and I as humans
wouldn't really care about.
And if you're sending an email or a text
message, whatever, it's just a typo.
It's not that big a deal.
It is going to be a big
deal to the computer.
A computer is going
to take you literally,
and if you don't finish your thought
in the way the language expects,
it's not going to
necessarily run at all.
So let's do this.
I'm going to go ahead here and
clear my screen down at the bottom
just so I can start fresh, and
I'm going to go ahead and run
this version of my program after
having made that change by deleting
the parenthesis.
I'm going to go ahead and type Python
again of Hello.py and this time
when I hit Enter, I'm hoping
I'm going to see hello, world,
but here we have an error on
the screen, a so-called syntax
error, which refers to my having
made a mistake at my keyboard.
And this one, fortunately,
is pretty straightforward.
It indeed says that this open
parenthesis was never closed.
And so that's probably pretty intuitive.
Now what I need to do, I need
to, of course, to close it.
Unfortunately, sometimes the error
messages we'll see in the coming weeks
are not going to be
nearly that user-friendly.
But there too again, with
experience, with practice, will you
get better at debugging such programs.
Let me now make sure that I
indeed fixed it correctly.
Let me go ahead and run now
Hello.py and hit Enter and, voila,
we're back in business.
Well let me pause here and see
if we have any questions now
about Python itself, writing, or running
even the simplest of these programs.
AUDIENCE: Could I write code inside a
word or, for example, Microsoft Excel?
And what's the barrier to doing that?
DAVID MALAN: A really
good question, and allow
me to very explicitly say
to the entire internet
that you should not write
code with Microsoft Word.
I mentioned that only
because it's a tool via which
you can write text and code is,
at the end of the day, just text.
But it's not the right tool for the job.
We don't need bold facing,
underlining, paragraphs and the like.
We generally want something much simpler
than Microsoft Word or Google Docs.
And so VS Code is an example of just
a more general purpose text editor.
Its purpose in life is to allow
you, the human, to edit text.
Nowadays these text editors
come with many more features.
In fact, you'll notice
that even in my code here,
even though it's just one line,
there's a bit of color to it.
The word "print" for me
is appearing in blue.
The parentheses are black.
And we'll see as we write more lines
of code, more and more of the lines
will come to life in various colors.
Now that's just one
feature of a text editor.
We'll see too that it has features
like this built-in terminal window.
It's going to have a built-in tool
for debugging or finding problems
with code.
And it's just a very
popular tool nowadays,
but there are many,
many others out there.
You're welcome to use them
for this course and beyond.
We just happen to use
this one in large part
too because you can also use VS
Code nowadays for free in the cloud.
How about one other question
here on programming with Python
or hello, world or
syntax more generally?
AUDIENCE: Yeah I was
trying to ask if it's not
possible to run the computer
using the terminal window?
DAVID MALAN: I think I heard is it not--
if it's possible to run the program
without the terminal window?
Are you--
AUDIENCE: Yes, sir.
DAVID MALAN: OK, you froze for me again.
But let me infer what the question is.
So in this environment, as
I've configured my computer,
I can only run these Python
programs via the terminal window.
Now that's good for me, the
programmer, or the person who's
trying to learn how to
program, but it's not very good
if you want to ship this software and
have other people use your actual code.
You can absolutely write programs
and then allow other people to use,
not a command line interface, but
a graphical user interface or GUI--
G-U-I. This is just one
mechanism and perhaps, I think,
the best one with which
to start writing code
because eventually it's going
to give us a lot more control.
Allow me to forge ahead
here, but please feel
free to continue asking questions
along the way if only via the chat.
Let's consider now how we might
go about improving this program.
Let's go about improving this program
to make it a little more interactive
and not just assume that everyone
is going to want to be greeted
more generically as hello, world.
Let's see if I can't get this program
to say something like Hello, David
or Hello, Jeremiah or Hello, Horatio
or whatever the actual user's name is.
Well to do this I'm going
to go back up to Hello to pi
and I'm going to add another line of
code at the very top that simply says,
for instance, what's your name, quote
unquote with an extra space at the end.
So I'm printing to the user asking
them a question for some input,
but now I need another function to
actually get input from the user.
And, perfectly, enough Python
comes with a function named input.
So here I'm going to go ahead and
call a function input, open paren,
close paren.
And that's going to prompt the user
with just a blinking cursor waiting
for them to type something in.
Now it turns out, if I read the
documentation for the input function,
it actually takes an argument itself.
I don't need to use "print" separately
and then prompt the user for input.
So I can actually simplify this
code before we even use it.
I'm going to go ahead here and
take that same string from print,
put it as an argument
to the input function,
and get rid of the "print" altogether.
And, in fact, that "print" would
have added a new line anyway.
So now I've just got a prompt
where the user's cursor is
going to end up blinking at the end of
the line asking them, what's your name?
In my terminal window I'm going
to run Python of Hello.py, Enter.
OK.
We're making progress.
It seems that this new function input
is indeed prompting me, the human,
for input.
So I'm going to type in my name--
David-- and hit Enter.
Unfortunately, it doesn't
really do anything with my name,
it just outputs it immediately.
All right, well, I
could fix this, right?
I could go up to line 2 and I
could change "world" to "David,"
and then back in my terminal window
here I can do Python of Hello.py, Enter.
What's your name?
David, Enter.
And there we go.
All right now I'm up and running.
Now my program is working as intended.
Of course, this isn't really
working as intended here.
Let me go ahead and try pretending
to be my colleague, Carter here.
Well Carter's name is this.
I'm going to go ahead and hit Enter and
I'll see, of course, Hello, Carter--
well, obviously not, because
I've hardcoded, so to speak,
I've written literally my
name inside of the string.
So we need some way now of actually
getting back what the user's input is
and doing something with it ultimately.
And for this we're going to leverage
another feature of programming,
specifically a feature of some
functions, which is that they
can have return values as well.
If you think of input as
being, again, this action,
this verb-- you can actually
personify it as maybe a person,
like a friend of yours that
you've asked a question of
and you've asked your friend to
go get input from someone else--
go ask that person their name.
And if your friend comes back
knowing that person's name, well,
wouldn't it be nice if they
handed that name back to you?
That's kind of what we need
metaphorically the function to do,
is get the user's input and then hand
it back to me so that I, the programmer,
can do something with it.
But if it's going to
be handed back to me,
I kind of want to put it somewhere
so that I can then print it back
on the screen.
I need to do the equivalent of take out
like a piece of paper or Post-It note,
write down on this piece of paper
what it is the human has said,
so that I can then feed it into
as input that print function.
And to do that, we're going to need
one more feature of programming, namely
variables.
And odds are, most everyone's familiar
with variables from math class
way back when-- x and
y and z and the like.
Well, programming has that
same capability, this ability
to create a variable-- in this
case, in the computer's memory--
not just on a piece of paper.
And that variable can store a value--
a number, some text, even
an image or video or more.
A variable is just a container for
some value inside of a computer
or inside of your own program.
So how do I go about
expressing myself in this way?
Well I think what I'm
going to do is introduce
a variable that's a little more
interestingly named than x or y.
I could just say this-- x = input.
But I'm going to use a better name than
a typical mathematical variable here
and I'm going to literally
call my variable "name," why?
Well in programming, because I have
a whole keyboard in front of me,
I can use more descriptive terms
to describe what it is I'm writing.
And now, though, there's an opportunity
to consider a specific piece of syntax.
We've seen parentheses, we've
seen quotes, all of which
are necessary when passing
inputs to a function,
but this equal sign here that's in
between input on the right and name
on the left is actually important.
And it's technically not
an equal sign per se.
It doesn't mean equality as
much as it means assignment.
So in Python and many
programming languages,
a single equal sign is
the assignment operator
and what that means
specifically is that, you
want to assign from right to left
whatever the user's input is.
So the equal sign copies from the
right to the left whatever the return
value of the function on the right is.
So again, the input function
clearly gets input from the user.
That's why I was able to type
my name or Carter's, but it also
sort of behind the scenes hands that
value, that return value, back to me
the programmer.
And if I use an equal sign and a
variable, no matter what I call it,
I can store that input in that
variable so as to reuse it later.
So now, sitting in the
computer's memory somewhere,
is a container containing "David"
quote, unquote or "Carter" quote,
unquote, or whatever
the human has typed in.
But here it's easy to make a mistake.
Suppose I decide to try
to print that name and so
I kind of on a hunch type
in this, hello, name.
Just kind of plugging in
the name of the variable.
Well let me go ahead here and run
Python of Hello.py and hit Enter.
That's going to prompt me for my name.
And let me type in my name--
D-A-V-I-D. But I haven't hit Enter yet.
And perhaps via the chat, what's going
to happen here when I now hit Enter?
I'm hoping it says, Hello, David.
I'd be OK if it says Hello, world, but I
don't want it to say what it's actually
going to say and, yep, what
we're seeing in the chat is,
well, it's probably going to
say literally Hello, name.
So that's not quite right.
So we need another way of printing
out the value inside of that variable
rather than just this word "name."
Well let me try this in a
couple of different ways.
Let me try this as follows--
let me go ahead and maybe undo this
because I've gotten pretty good already
at saying Hello.
So let's draw that line in the
sand and just say, all right,
let's get at least get
Hello comma out the door.
Let's now print name and just on
a hunch, I'm going to try this.
I'm going to use print again--
because you can use these functions
as many times as you need--
and I'm going to pass to the print
function the variable called name.
But notice I'm being
a little clever now.
I'm not putting it in double quotes
because we've seen already that double
quotes means literally
print out N-A-M-E.
I'm getting rid of the quotes
this time in hopes that,
now by passing the variable called name
to the function called print it will,
in fact, go about printing the
contents of that variable that is,
its so-called value.
All right, let's go
ahead and do this here.
Python of Hello.py, Enter.
What's your name?
David.
And now, crossing my fingers
still, I see Hello comma David.
All right.
So it's not the best program.
I'm kind of cutting some
corners here, so to speak.
I'm saying Hello, David
on two separate lines.
So it's not as elegant,
it's not as pretty,
it's not as grammatically appropriate
in English as just saying it
all in one breath on one line, but at
least I've solved the problem, just not
very well yet.
But let me take a step back
now and perhaps introduce
a couple of other concepts with
which we should be familiar,
which is as our programs get longer and
they're no longer just one line or two
or even three, eventually our programs
are going to become dozens of lines,
maybe even hundreds of lines long.
Let's set the stage for
success moving forward.
It turns out that Python and
a lot of programming languages
also support something called comments.
Comments are notes to
yourself in your code
and you include comments by way
of a special symbol-- in Python
it's going to be the
hash symbol, typically--
and that allows you to
write the equivalent
of a note to yourself but in a way
that's not going to break your code.
The computer actually
ignores your comment.
It's just there for you, it's
just there for your teacher,
it's just there for
your colleague with whom
you're sharing ultimately that code.
So if I go back to VS
Code here and I just
want to add some comments to this
program to explain to my teacher,
to myself, to my colleagues
what this program is doing,
well, let's go ahead and do that.
I'm going to go at the very
top of my program and on line 1
now I'm going to move that
original line of code down a bit,
I'm going to add a hash, and I'm
going to say something like this,
ask user for their name.
Now, I don't have to use that language.
I don't have to use that text.
I could use any human
language whatsoever.
It doesn't have to be English.
But I'm going to now, below that,
just say something like this--
say Hello to user.
And you'll notice that
VS Code by default
is kind of graying out my comments.
They're no longer blue, there's
no red, there's no color in them.
And that's just because
they're notes to myself
and the computer ultimately
is going to ignore them.
But what we have now is
two comments-- ask user
for their name and then a second
comment, say Hello to user.
And I've just kind of
commented each chunk of code,
like each line or lines plural of code,
that are doing something noteworthy.
Why?
Well, tomorrow morning
when I wake up having
slept for quite some time, forgotten
what it is I did the previous day,
it's convenient with
comments to just see
in English or your own
human language what
it is this program is doing so that
you don't have to read the code itself
and, better yet, if there's
maybe a mistake down the road,
you can read what your intention was
and then you can look at the code
and figure out if your code is
now doing what you intended.
So this isn't really necessary
for a program this small.
It's pretty obvious with just
one or two or three lines
what the program is doing.
It's just as fast to read
the code than the comments,
but getting into this habit
is generally a good thing--
to comment your code every one or a
few lines so as to remind yourself
and others what it is your
intent and your code is doing.
What's nice about comments too is this--
comments can also serve to be
sort of a to-do list for yourself.
There's this notion in
programming of pseudocode.
Pseudocode isn't a formal thing.
It's not one specific language.
It's just using English
or your own human language
to express your thoughts succinctly,
methodically, algorithmically,
so to speak.
But pseudocode, therefore,
because it's not Python
and it's not necessarily
English, it just kind of allows
you to outline your
program even in advance.
So for instance, if I
wasn't sure today how
I wanted to go about
writing this program
but I didn't know what I wanted
to do, I could have started today
by just writing this in Hello.py.
No code, I could have written just
a couple of comments to myself--
Step 1, ask user for their name.
Step 2, say Hello to user.
Then once I've outlined my program
in pseudocode, then I can go in there
and say, all right, how do I
ask the user for their name?
Well, I can do input
"what's your name" question?
And then on the left here, I can maybe
put a variable and assign it to that.
OK, how do I say Hello to the user?
Well, I know I can use print
to say things on the screen.
Let me say hello, and let me--
OK, let me now print the person's name.
So again, pseudocode is a nice way
of structuring your to-do list,
especially if you have no
idea how to write the code,
because it breaks a bigger program
down into small bite-sized tasks.
All right, let me pause
here to see if there are now
any questions on comments, pseudocode,
return values, or variables.
Any questions we can clear up here?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, my question
is does the function input
work for any type of
information, or only for words?
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, really good question.
So according to its documentation, and
we'll look more at formal documentation
soon, input is going
to expect what's called
a string, that is a
sequence of text, be it
in English or any other human language.
But it's indeed going to be expecting
text with which to prompt the user.
A good question.
How about another question
from the group, if we could?
AUDIENCE: I wanted to ask how would
I make a several line comment?
DAVID MALAN: Oh, how do you
do many lines of comments,
if I'm hearing you correctly?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
DAVID MALAN: Sure.
You would just keep
doing them like this.
You just prefix each of the lines with
a hash symbol, like I'm doing here.
There is another technique for doing
multi-line comments in Python that
actually tend to have special meaning.
You can do three double quotes like
this and then anything in between here
is a comment.
That's another technique.
Or you can use single quotes as well.
But more on those, I
think, another time.
All right, well, you don't
mind, let me forge ahead here
and see how we might
improve this program further
and also introduce a few
other features that we might
want to take into account over time.
So it turns out that we can
certainly improve on this program
because it's a little disappointing
that I'm cutting this corner
and saying Hello comma and then
on a new line printing out name.
Like we can do better.
And most programs you use on your
phone or your laptop certainly
keep text together when people want.
So how can we go about doing that?
Well there's a few different ways.
And in fact, the goal here is not
so much to solve this one problem,
but to demonstrate and
emphasize that in programming--
Python and other languages--
there's so many ways
sometimes to solve the same problem.
And here's one way to
solve this problem.
Let me go in here and let me
go ahead now and say hello,
and let me just add to the
end of that the user's name.
So I'm using + in kind
of an interesting way.
This is not addition, per se.
I'm not adding numbers,
obviously, but I do
kind of want to add the person's name
to the string of text Hello comma.
Well let me go now down to my terminal
window and run Python of Hello.py
again, Enter.
What's your name?
I'm going to type in David.
Enter.
OK, it's better.
It's better, but there's a minor
bug, albeit aesthetic here.
There's missing space, but let's
just use some intuition here.
Well, if I'm missing the
space after the comma,
why don't I go ahead and
just add it manually here.
Let me now rerun the program Python
of Hello.py, Enter, David, Enter.
And there we go.
Now we have something that
looks a little prettier
in terms of English grammar.
Hello, comma, space, David.
And now if we rewind, you
might have noticed before
or wondered why I had this seemingly
extra space after my question mark,
namely here.
There's a space after the question
mark but before the double quote
and that was just for aesthetics too.
I wanted to move the user's
cursor one space to the right
so that when I typed their
name or they typed their name,
it's not immediately next to
that same question mark there.
But there's other ways we can do this.
It turns out that some
functions, print among them,
actually take multiple arguments.
And it turns out that if
you separate the inputs
to a function-- the so-called
arguments to a function-- with a comma,
you can pass in not just one, but
two, three, four, five, onward.
So let me go ahead and pass in not just
hello, comma, space, but that followed
by name.
And this is a little confusing
potentially at first glance
because now I've got two commas
but it's important to note
that the first comma is inside of
my quotation marks, which is simply
an English grammatical thing.
The second comma here is
outside of the quotes,
but between what are now two
separate arguments to print.
The first argument is
hello, comma, space.
The second argument is
the name variable itself.
So let's see how this looks.
Python of Hello.py, Enter.
What's your name?
David.
Enter.
OK, I've kind of over-corrected.
Now I've got two spaces for some reason.
Well, it turns out, and
this is subtle, when
you pass multiple arguments to print, it
automatically inserts a space for you.
This was not relevant
earlier because I was
passing in one big argument to print
all at once by using that + operator.
This time I'm passing in
two because of the comma.
So if I don't want that extra space,
I don't need to pass in one myself,
I can just do this and now notice,
if I run this program again--
Python of Hello.py,
type in my name David,
now it looks grammatically
like I might want.
Now which of these approaches is better?
This approach uses a function
print with two arguments--
Hello, comma and the name variable.
The previous version, recall,
technically used one argument,
even though it looked a little curious.
It's one argument in the sense that
the computer, just like mathematicians,
are going to do what's
inside of parentheses first.
So if inside of parentheses
you have this string of text--
hello, comma, and a space,
which I need to add back.
Then you have a +, which
means not addition, per se,
but concatenation-- to join the thing
on the left and the thing on the right.
This ultimately becomes
the English phrase--
Hello, comma, space, David.
And then what's being passed
ultimately to the function
is technically something like this,
but it's doing it all dynamically.
It's not me typing in David
as I discreetly did earlier.
It's figuring out dynamically what
that value is after concatenating Hello
with the value of name and
then passing that ultimately
to print as the sole argument.
Let me pause here to see if there's
any questions on numbers of arguments
now to functions.
AUDIENCE: Can we use
a function many times
to solve a certain problem which we
can encounter many times in our code?
DAVID MALAN: You can.
You can use a function many different
times to solve some problem.
What we'll soon see, though,
is if you find yourself
as the programmer solving a
problem the same way again,
and again, and again,
it turns out you'll
be able to make your
own function so that you
don't have to keep reusing the basic
ones that come with the language.
AUDIENCE: I was curious about
the comma and the + sign.
So after + sign, can we give just
one variable and after comma again we
give multiple variable status?
What is the difference?
DAVID MALAN: A good question.
So in the context of strings--
and I keep using that term.
"String" is a technical term
in a programming language
and again, it means a sequence of text--
a character, a word, a whole paragraph,
even.
So the + operator is
not just used, as we'll
see, for addition of numbers in
Python, like we do on paper pencil,
but it also is used for concatenation
of strings on the left and the right.
If you did want to combine
not just two strings--
left and right-- but
a third and a fourth,
you can absolutely keep using +,
+, +, +, and chain them together
just like in math.
Eventually that's going to
start to look a little ugly,
I dare say, especially if
your line of code gets long.
So there's better ways that
we'll actually soon see.
And a good question as well.
Well let me come back to
the code here in question
and see if we can show you
just a couple of other ways
to solve the same problem, along the way
emphasizing that what we're technically
talking about here, yes, are
strings, but there's even
a technical term for
these strings in Python,
it's just STR, so to speak,
S-T-R for short, for string.
As you may know if you
programmed in other languages,
people who invent programming languages
like to be very succinct, to the point,
so we tend to use fairly short
phrases to describe things,
not necessarily full words.
So while you might say
"string," technically
in Python what we're really talking
about, these sequences of text,
are technically STRs.
This is an actual type
of data in a program.
But we'll soon see that there's other
types of data in programs as well.
In fact, let's see if we can't
improve this in one other way.
I like the progress we've made by
keeping everything on the same line--
Hello, David all on the same line.
What more though could we do in
terms of solving this problem?
Well, it turns out that we
didn't have to give up entirely
with using print twice.
Let me rewind a little bit and
go back to that earlier version
where I wasn't really sure how to solve
this problem so I was using print once
to print out just the Hello
and the space and the comma.
And then I used print
again to print name.
That's, strictly speaking, wasn't bad,
but there was this visual side effect
that I didn't like.
It just looked ugly to have
these two lines of text separate
from one another.
But there's another way to fix this.
Clearly it seems to be the case that
the print function is automatically
outputting a blank line.
It's moving the cursor automatically
for me to the next line
because that's why I'm seeing
Hello on one line and David
on the next and then my prompt--
the dollar sign-- on
the line below that.
So print seems to be
presuming automatically
that you want it to move
the cursor to the next line
after you pass it some argument.
But you can override that behavior.
Again, functions take arguments
which influence their behavior,
you just have to know
what those arguments are.
And it turns out that if we look at
the documentation for Python's print
function, we can actually
look up at this URL here--
docs.python.org is where all of
Python's official documentation lies.
If I poke around, I can find my
way to more specifically this URL
here where I can find all of the
available functions in Python
and the documentation there for.
And if I go a little more
precisely, I can even
find specific documentation
for the print function itself.
And rather than pull
that up in a browser,
I'm going to go ahead and highlight
just one line from that same URL, which
is this, and this is easily the
most cryptic thing we've seen yet,
but this is the official
documentation for the print function.
And one of the best things you can do
when learning a programming language
is, honestly, learn to
read the documentation,
because truly, all of the answers
to your questions will in some way
be there, even though, admittedly,
it's not always obvious.
And I will say too,
Python's documentation
isn't necessarily the easiest thing,
especially for a first time or novice
programmer.
It too just takes practice, so try
not to get overwhelmed if you're not
sure what you're looking at.
But let me walk you
through this example.
This again is a line of text from
Python's official documentation
for the print function.
What this indicates as follows is this--
the name of this function
is, of course print.
Then there's a parenthesis over here
and another close parenthesis way
over there.
Everything inside of
those parentheses are
the arguments, the potential
arguments, to the function.
However, when we're
looking at these arguments
in the documentation like this,
there's technically a different term
that we would use.
These are technically the
parameters to the function.
So when you're talking about
what you can pass to a function
and what those inputs are
called, those are parameters.
When you actually use
the function and pass
in values inside of those
parentheses, those inputs,
those values are arguments.
So we're talking about the exact same
thing-- parameters and arguments are
effectively the same
thing, but the terms you
use from looking at the problem
from different directions.
When we're looking at what the
function can take versus what
you're actually passing
into the function.
So what does this imply?
Well this syntax is pretty
cryptic, but at the moment,
just know that an asterisk, a
star, and then the word "objects"
means that the print function
can take any number of objects.
You can pass in 0 strings
of text, one string
like I did, two strings like I did,
or, technically, infinitely many
if you really want, though that
code is not going to look very good.
After that we see a comma, then
we see another parameter here
called SEP, short for
separator in English.
And notice the equal sign and the
single quote, space, single quote.
So 'space' I don't
know what that is yet,
but I think we've seen a hint about it.
Let's focus though
for a moment on this--
the print function takes another
parameter called end and the default
value of that parameter is apparently,
based on this equal sign and these
quotes, /n.
And what is /n, if you'd
like to chime in in the chat?
Anyone who's program before
has probably seen this,
though if you've never programmed
before, this might look quite cryptic.
Backslash n means new line,
and it's a way textually
of indicating if and when you
want the computer effectively
to move the cursor to the next
line, create a new line of text.
And so technically, if we
read into the documentation,
we'll see more detail on this.
The fact that there's a parameter called
end in the documentation for the print
function, just means that by default
this print function is going to end
every line with /n.
You don't literally see
/n, you see a new line.
You see the cursor
moving to the next line.
Now by that logic, let's move backwards.
SEP four separator-- the
default value of separator
is apparently a single blank space.
Well where have we seen that?
Well recall in an earlier example
when I passed in not just one but two
arguments to the print function.
Recall that they magically
had a space between them.
In fact, they had that
space + my own space
and that's why I deleted my space
because at that point it was extra.
So this just means that when you pass
multiple arguments to print, by default
they're going to be
separated by a single space.
By default, when you
pass arguments to print,
it's the whole thing is going
to be ended with a new line.
Now just by knowing this,
and let me literally
wave my hand at the rest of the
documentation for another day,
there's more things that
print can do, but we're
going to focus just on SEP and on END,
let's see if we can't leverage this now
to solve that original problem.
The original problem was this,
I don't like how Hello, David
is on two different lines.
Well that's happening again
because print is automatically
printing out a new line, so
let's tell it not to do that.
Let's tell it by passing a second
argument to the first use of PRINT
to say END = quote, unquote--
not /n, which is the
default automatically.
Let's make it quote,
unquote nothing else.
Let's override the default
value so there is no new line.
There's literally nothing there.
And let's see what happens.
Let me now go down to my
terminal window and clear it.
And I'm going to run
Python of Hello.py, Enter.
I'm going to type in
my name, David and I
think now everything is going to
stay on the same line because--
and it did-- this line here, 5, is
going to print out Hello, comma, space,
but then nothing at
the end of it because I
changed it to be quote, unquote.
The second line is going
to print the name, David,
or whatever the human's name is, and it
will move the cursor to the next line
because I didn't override
the value of END there.
Just to see this more explicitly,
if you do something cryptic like,
well I have no idea what's going on.
Let me just put in temporarily
three question marks here.
We'll see the results of this too.
Let me go back down to my terminal
window, run Python of hello. py,
what's your name?
David.
And now you see literally
really ugly output,
but you see literally what's going on.
Hello, comma, space, then three question
marks, END, that print statement,
and then you see D-A-V-I-D.
So not a good outcome,
but it demonstrates just how
much control we have here too.
And let me rewind further.
Recall that in our
other version of this,
when I passed in Hello, comma and name,
they were separated by a single space.
So Python of Hello.py, D-A-V-I-D, Enter.
That just worked.
Well what if we override the
value of SEP for separator?
Instead of being one space,
we could say something
like, question mark, question
mark, question mark just to wrap
our minds around what's going on there.
Let me now do Python of
Hello.py, D-A-V-I-D, Enter.
And you see two.
These two inputs--
Hello, comma and the name are
now separated in an ugly way
by three question marks because I've
overridden the default behavior of SEP.
And even though the
documentation uses single quotes,
I've been in the habit
of using double quotes.
In Python you can use either.
Strictly speaking, it doesn't
matter, but you should be consistent
and I generally always
use double quotes.
Python's documentation, though,
always uses single quotes.
Questions now on these
types of parameters?
And allow me to propose that
we give these an official name.
Up until now, when we've
been passing values to print,
those are called positional
parameters-- positional in the sense
that the first thing you pass
to print gets printed first.
The second thing you pass to print
after a comma gets printed second.
And so forth.
But there's also these things we've
now seen called named parameters.
Named SEP, separator, or END,
E-N-D for the line ending.
Those are named parameters
because one, they're optional
and you can pass them in at the
end of your print statement,
but you can also use them by name.
AUDIENCE: This may be a weird
question, but I was wondering,
what if someone wants to add actually
quotation marks within the quotation
marks?
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, I like how you think.
This is what we would
call a corner case, right?
Just when we've made--
right, this is all
sounding great, at least as
programming goes, but, wait a minute,
what if you want to print a quote?
That's a really good question.
Well, let's see if we
can't figure this out.
Suppose that I want to print
out not just the user's name.
Let me simplify this further.
Let me go ahead and get
rid of a lot of this,
and let me just say
something like, Hello--
maybe I'm being a little sarcastic here.
Hello, (sarcastically) "friend."
You know, in that kind of tone.
Well this is not going
to work, actually,
because you are trying to use quotes
to be like "friend" in finger quotes,
but you're also trying
to end the sentence.
And if I try running
this, let's do this.
Python of Hello.py, you'll see
that this is just invalid syntax.
Perhaps you forgot a comma.
And this is actually a bit annoying.
Sometimes the error messages
you see are misleading.
Like the computer, the
language, doesn't really
know what's going on
so it gives its best
guess, but it's not necessarily correct.
But I can solve this
problem in a couple of ways.
I can do this--
I can change my outermost
quotes to single quotes.
Because recall a moment
again, I said you
could use double quotes or single
quotes so long as you're consistent.
So that's fine.
If you use single quotes
on the outside, you
can then use double quotes on the
inside and you'll see them literally.
So for instance, if I run
Python of Hello.py, there we go.
Hello, "friend."
But there's another way.
If you insist on using double
quotes as you might want to,
just to be consistent, you can also
use that backslash character again.
We saw the /n a moment ago.
And that meant we don't want a
literal n to be in the output,
we wanted a new line.
So the backslash actually represents
what's called an escape character.
An escape character is
one that you can't just
type necessarily once on your keyboard.
You need to express it
with multiple characters.
So I can actually put backslashes in
front of these inner double quotes
so that the computer
realizes, Oh wait a minute,
those aren't quotes that finish or start
the thought, they're literal quotes.
So now let me go back to my terminal
window, run Python of Hello.py, Enter.
And now it's working as well.
So escaping is a general technique
that allows us to do that too.
And if I may, let me rewind
now on these examples
and go back to where we
left off with my code,
I'm just undoing all of that, because
I want to get back to the point
ultimately of specifying now a
final way of solving this problem.
Well, it turns out that
we have yet another way
we can solve this problem, which
is perhaps the most frequently done
now or at least the most elegant
when it comes to setting us up
for longer and longer uses of strings.
You can use a relatively new feature
of Python that allows you to do this.
You can literally put, not the name of
the variable like that in your string,
because we already saw
this is wrong, right?
If you do this, you will
literally see Hello, comma, name.
But what if I do this?
What if I put curly braces or curly
brackets around the variable's name?
Notice VS Code is actually very
subtly changing the color of it.
So VS Code knows something
interesting is going on here.
Let me run this program, but I'm not
done yet Python of Hello.py, Enter.
D-A-V-I-D, Enter.
OK, obviously not what I want,
but I need to tell Python
that this is a special string.
This is what we're going to call
a format string or an F string,
a relatively new feature of
Python in the past few years
that tells Python to actually format
stuff in the string in a special way.
And the symbol via what you
do this is a little weird,
but this is what the world chose.
If you put an F at the
beginning of the string,
right before the first quote mark,
that's a clue to Python that, ooh,
this is a special string.
Let me format this in
a special way for you.
Let me now rerun the program.
Python Hello.py, Enter.
D-A-V-I-D, Enter.
And now we see the
goal this whole time--
Hello, David.
We don't start with this way, because
I think if we did this the first way,
you'd be like, why are we doing this?
What are all these magical symbols?
But this is just yet another
way to solve the same problem.
But let me propose that
we consider now yet
other things we can do with strings.
And it turns out that even as we've been
doing some relatively simple operations
here, we've generally been trusting
that the user is going to cooperate
and that is to say that they're going
to actually type in what we want them
to type.
Now just because they type a
string, though, doesn't mean
it's going to look the way we want.
You and I, honestly,
as humans are actually
in the habit-- on websites and
apps-- of like accidentally hitting
the spacebar a lot, either
at the beginning of our input
or at the end, maybe because the
space bar tends to be so big.
It's pretty common to
get accidental spaces
before or after some users' input.
You and I are definitely in the habit
of not necessarily capitalizing words
like we should.
If we're sending text messages,
we're probably being a little quick
and just sending
everything in lowercase,
for instance, if that's your style,
if your phone's not fixing it for you.
Maybe in a formal letter you
would capitalize things properly.
But you and I as humans, we can't really
be trusted to type things in a nice way
necessarily when using
some piece of software,
be it an app or a website
or something else.
But it turns out that
strings themselves come
with a lot of built-in functionality.
You can see all of that in
Python's own documentation here.
The string data type that
we've been talking about
comes with a lot of
functionality built in that
means that we can manipulate the
user's input to do more than just
join it with something else like
Hello, we can actually clean it up
or reformat it in a way that hopefully
looks a little better for us.
So let me go back to my
code here and let me just
demonstrate what might happen
if a user doesn't cooperate.
If I go ahead here and run
Python of Hello.py, Enter.
Let me just sloppily hit the
spacebar a few too many times.
Why?
I just wasn't paying attention.
And now I'm going to type in my
name D-A-V-I-D and, I don't know,
I hit the spacebar a couple more times.
Like it's kind of a mess.
It's all lowercase.
That's not going to necessarily
look grammatically right.
It's got spaces here and here.
The program is going
to print exactly that
and that looks really
bad, at least if we're
prioritizing aesthetics and grammar.
Like, why are there so many
spaces after the comma?
This is not a very nice
way to greet your users.
But we can clean this up.
It turns out that built into strings,
which, again, is this data type, so
to speak, this type of data in Python--
is the ability to actually
do things to that string.
So let me do this, I can actually go
ahead and do something like this--
name = name.strip.
And what does this do?
Remove white space from string.
And what do I mean by this?
Well, on the right-hand
side, notice I've
written the variable name called Name.
I've then used a period
or a dot, and then I
seem to be doing what's
a function, right?
Any time we've seen a function thus
far, we see the function's name-- print
or input, then we see a parenthesis,
then another parenthesis,
and that's exactly what I see here.
But I'm using this function
a little differently.
Technically, this function is--
in this context-- called a method.
And what do I mean by that?
Well, if Name is a string, a.k.a.
STR, well it turns out,
according to the documentation,
there's a lot of functions that
come with strings in Python.
And you can access that
functionality by using
the name of a string like literally
name here, then a period, then the name
of the, function and then an open
parenthesis and a closed parenthesis.
Maybe some arguments inside of
those parentheses, but in this case,
it doesn't need any arguments.
I just want to strip the space
from the left and the space
from the right of the user's input.
But that's not enough.
I want to remember
that I've stripped off
that white space on
the left and the right,
so I'm going to use the
equal sign again here.
And notice that just as before,
this doesn't mean equality,
this means assignment
from right to left.
So when this line of
code here-- name.strip--
returns to me, a.k.a.
a return value, it will
return the same thing
that the user typed in, but with
no more white space to the left
or to the white [CHUCKLES] to the right.
So then the equal sign
assignment is going
to copy that value from
the right to the left,
thereby updating the value
inside of my name variable.
So you can not only assign
values to variables,
you can absolutely change
the value of variables
by just using the assignment
operator, the equal sign again,
and again, and again, and it
will just keep copying from right
to left whatever the
new value should be.
So now if I rerun this program,
Python of Hello.py, Enter.
I have D-A-V-I-- oop, let's do it again.
Space, space, space, space, space.
d-a-v-i-d in all lowercase, space,
space, Enter.
It's better.
It hasn't fixed my
capitalization, so I'm still
being a little sloppy with the
first D, But it has stripped off
all of that extra space.
Super minor detail, right?
Like this isn't all that
exciting, but it just
speaks to the power of what you can
do with just a single line of code.
Now what else can I do here?
Well I could capitalize
the user's input.
Let me go ahead and try this.
It turns out that I could also
do this-- name.capitalize.
So let me go ahead and
capitalize user's name.
And again, I'm making
comments and there's
no one right way to write the comments.
I'm just using some short
English phrases here
to remind myself of what I'm doing.
What's now going on here?
Well let me go ahead and run
Python of Hello.py, Enter.
Space, space, space, space, space,
d-a-v-i-d, space, space, Enter.
OK.
Now it's looking prettier, right?
No matter how the user typed in
their name, even a little sloppily,
I'm now fixing that.
But let's try something.
I'm getting a little curious here.
How about this?
Space, space, space, space,
space, d-a-v-i-d space m-a-l-a-n--
I'll use my last name now--
Enter.
OK, so ironically, "capitalize" is not
really capitalizing everything we want.
It's clearly capitalizing what?
Just the very first letter.
So it turns out that, again,
there's other functions in Python
that come with strings.
And if we poke around the documentation,
scrolling through a URL like that,
I bet we'll find another solution,
one of which is actually this.
Let's actually change this to title.
There's yet another function
that comes with strings
called Title that do
title-based capitalization, just
like a book or a person's
name, capitalizing
the first letter of each word.
And this is just going to do
a little more work for us.
So let's go ahead and run this.
And as an aside, I'm kind
of tired now at this point
of typing Python, Python,
Python all the time.
It turns out that when using a
command line interface like this,
you can actually go back through
all of your old commands.
What I just did a moment
ago was I hit the up arrow.
That immediately goes back through
my history of all of the commands
I've ever typed.
So this is just a faster way
now for me to repeat myself
than typing everything manually.
Let me go ahead and hit Enter,
space, space, space, space, space,
d-a-v-i-d m-a-l-a-n space,
space, all lowercase, Enter.
Now it's looking better.
Now I've capitalized things
and cleaned things up.
But what about my code?
I've got like eight lines
of code now, four of which
are comments, four of
which are actual code.
Do I really need this much?
Well, not necessarily.
Watch what I can also do in Python.
Let me not bother capitalizing
the user's name separately.
Let me say this--
and capitalize user's name.
I can chain these functions together.
I can add Title to the end of this.
And now what's happening?
Well again, with a
line of code like this,
you first focus on what's to
the right of the equal sign,
then we'll get to the
left of the equal sign.
What's on the right of the equals sign?
This line here.
Well what does this mean?
Get the value of the name variable,
like D-A-V-I-D space, M-A-L-A-N.
Then strip off the white space
on the left and the right.
That is going to return a value.
It's going to return D-A-V-I-D space
M-A-L-A-N without any white space
to the left or right.
What do you want to do
with that return value?
You want Python to
title case it, that is
go through every word
in that resulting string
and fix the first letter of the
first word, the first letter
of the second word, and so forth.
And then-- now we can
finish our thought--
copy the whole thing from right to
left into that same name variable.
And you know what?
I can take this even one step further.
Why don't we go ahead
and do this if we want.
Let me get rid of all of that,
and let me just do strip and title
all on that first line.
And now we've gone from like
eight lines of code to four.
It's a lot tighter.
It's a lot neater.
And even though reasonable
people might disagree,
it's arguably better because
it's just easier to read.
Fewer lines of code, fewer
opportunities for mistakes,
it just allows me to move on
with my next problem to solve.
All right, let me pause here and see if
there's any questions on these methods.
A method is a function that's
built in to a type of value,
like these functions are.
Or on F strings which
we saw a moment ago.
AUDIENCE: Yes, hi.
Thanks, David.
So is there a way to remove
the spaces between the spaces
that I might have added?
DAVID MALAN: Short answer, no.
If you read the documentation
at that same URL earlier,
you'll see that strip removes from the
left and the right, but not in between.
In fact, there's two other
functions that come with strings.
One is called L strip, the
other is called R strip,
that allow you to do one or the other.
If we want to start getting
rid of space in the middle,
we're going to have to do a
different trick altogether.
AUDIENCE: How many functions can be
combine like this dot strip, dot title,
all combined.
So how many we can combine?
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, a
really good question.
Technically, as many as
you want, but at some point
your code is going to start to
look really, really bad, right?
Because the line of code is
going to get really, really long.
It's eventually going to maybe
wrap around again and again.
So at some point, you just kind of
say like, uh-uh, that's too many.
And you start breaking it up
into multiple lines like I did.
Maybe reassigning the value
to the variable as needed.
And this is actually a good question.
If I can pivot, [INAUDIBLE] off your
question, I mean, what do people think?
If we could go ahead and put
everyone's hands down for a moment.
Let me ask this--
is the way I've done this now,
with strip and title and input
all in the same line--
better than my previous approach?
In Zoom you can use the
Yes icon or the No icon.
If you think this version
is better, say Yes.
If you think this previous
version was better, for instance,
this one here where we had
everything broken out, say No.
And then we'll see why in just a moment.
I proposed earlier that
reasonable people can disagree
and that's absolutely the case.
Doing it one way or the
other isn't necessarily best,
at least if you can justify it.
Let me go back to the
most recent version here.
All right so we're seeing a
lot of Yeses and a lot of Nos.
Why don't we go ahead and call
on one of the Yeses, if we could.
Someone who's voting Yes, why do you
think the current version of this code
is indeed better than the previous
longer version of the code?
AUDIENCE: I think it's more readable.
So I can say, this is the name variable.
It gets some input and then remove
the space and give it a title.
And there you go.
You have a hello, name.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, I think
that's pretty reasonable.
It's very readable, at least
if you're in the habit,
as you are in English,
of reading left to right.
It just kind of flows very
naturally as a result.
The lines is not really that long.
It's certainly fitting
nicely onto the screen.
So I think that's a good argument.
How about a counterpoint, though?
Someone who voted No, if we could call
on someone who thinks this is worse.
AUDIENCE: Because it's
not readable at all.
It seems like it's a very long line.
So I think it's better to separate.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
I think that's persuasive too, right?
It's getting a little longer.
And even though my sentence here--
what's your name-- is relatively short,
you could imagine that this
could get even uglier quickly
if I were asking a longer
question of the user, that's
going to make this line of code even
longer and therefore less readable.
It might be less obvious to me or my
colleagues that I am calling strip
or that I am calling title.
It might be kind of an
unexpected surprise.
So I think that's reasonable too.
In short, there is no right answer here.
And in fact, part of the process
of getting better at programming
is getting your own sense of
style or working for a company
where they might prescribe which
way is better than the other
because they just want
everyone doing the same thing,
even though reasonable
people might disagree.
Ultimately though, so
long as you have what's
a pretty good argument in favor of
one way or the other, like ultimately,
that's what's important.
If you're just doing things because you
don't really know which one is better,
that's not great.
But if and when you
start to acquire opinions
and if your boss, if your teacher,
if your colleague, your friend,
can challenge you and say, wait,
why did you do it like this?
They might not agree with you,
but at least have an answer,
and that should be sufficiently
persuasive in general.
Now, strings come with a
whole bunch of other methods
as well, among which is one called
split, which can, as the name suggests,
split a string into multiple
smaller substrings, so to speak.
For instance, if the
human here is in the habit
of typing in their first name, then
a space, and then their last name,
and you want to go ahead and
greet them only by first name,
well we could actually
leverage that single space
between the first name and
last name and split that string
into two smaller substrings.
How can we do this?
Well, let me go ahead and
in between these lines
proactively comment that
we're about to split user's
name into first name and last name.
And then let's go ahead and take that
name variable, which currently contains
something like, presumably,
David, space, Malan,
and let me go ahead and call
split and pass in as the argument
to split a single white space,
thereby indicating that I indeed
want to split on that character
Now it turns out split is going to
return a sequence of values, ideally
a first name and then a last name.
And we can actually, in Python,
assign both of those values
from that sequence at
once to some variables.
For instance, first comma
last equals, and that's
going to have the effect
from right to left
of putting the first such value in the
first variable, the second such value
in the second variable.
So now on my last line of
code, I can go in and say hello
not to the full name,
something like David Malan,
I can just say Hello, first.
All right, let's go ahead and clear my
terminal window, run Python of Hello.py
and hit Enter.
I won't bother with any leading white
space this time, but let me go ahead
and type in David space Malan, and
crossing my fingers as usual, Hello,
David is what we now see.
All right, so we've seen so much,
so many examples thus far involving
strings, but certainly programs
and programming languages can
manipulate other types of data as well.
Let's go ahead and transition then
to another very common type of data
in Python, in programming
more generally, namely
integers, otherwise
known in Python as INT--
I-N-T. So just as STR, S-T-R is
short for string, so is INT in Python
short for integer.
Well, what's an integer?
Well just like in math it's
a number like negative 2,
negative 1, 0, 1, 2, and all the
way toward negative infinity, all
the way toward positive infinity.
But there's no decimal
point in an integer.
It's just a number like negative
2, negative 1, 0, 1, and 2 onward.
That's an INT.
Of course, in the world of mathematics,
there's lots of symbols that we use.
And we've seen + before, although
we used it for a different purpose.
But Python supports
these symbols and more.
And Python allows you to
add numbers together +,
subtract numbers, multiply
numbers, divide numbers.
And the only one here that might look a
little strange to people or unfamiliar
is this percent sign, but it doesn't
mean percent in this context.
If you use a single percent
sign in a Python program,
that's actually the
so-called modulo operator,
the operator that allows you to
take the remainder after dividing
one number by another.
So we'll see examples of that before
long, but the first four of these
are perhaps quite, quite familiar.
Well it turns out that in
Python you cannot necessarily--
you don't necessarily have to keep
writing code in a file like Hello.py
and then running it
in a terminal window.
One of the features that
many people like about Python
is that it supports this
so-called interactive mode.
Like you can start writing Python
code and immediately execute
each of those lines
interactively, especially
if you don't care about saving
all of your lines of code.
You just want to execute code
and get back some answers.
So for instance, let me go back to VS
Code here and let me close Hello.py
and let me click on the little triangle
over here in my terminal window just
to make it much bigger just
temporarily for a moment.
So I'm not creating any .py file now,
I'm just going to run Python by itself
at my prompt.
And you'll see when I do this, I
get some cryptic looking output
and the date and time at which the
program was last updated, and so forth.
But I ultimately get three
triple brackets like this.
Is the interactive mode for Python.
So I'm running the Python interpreter
and any time I type a line of code
in the interpreter, it's going
to execute it immediately.
I don't have to keep running
Python again and again.
It's as though in the
human world, if you
were standing next to a human
who speaks some other language,
and you're just having a conversation
with them back and forth,
it's all happening-- the
translation-- immediately.
So what might I do in interactive mode?
Well I could do something
like 1 + 1, Enter.
That's actually code, all right?
You might not think of it as code,
but if a bit of arithmetic and you
know numbers, and you know
+, that's valid Python code.
And you can use Python
really as a fancy calculator.
But I could do other things too.
If I want to print to
myself Hello, world,
I can also print out that
line of code there too--
Hello, world.
So it's interactive in
the sense that the moment
you execute a line of code,
boom, you see the result.
We're generally not going to
do that because at least when
teaching the language, we tend to
want to do things incrementally
and we want you to be able to
see where it is we came from.
And we want to be able to try
things again and again, especially
if we make mistakes.
But know that this is
indeed a feature of Python,
this so-called interactive mode.
But let's focus for a moment now,
not just on that interactivity,
but really on the fact
that Python apparently
supports integers and mathematics
and some of those basic operations.
And let's see if we can't make
maybe our own little calculator.
So let me go ahead and
open up VS Code again,
and I'm going to shrink
down my terminal window,
and I'm going to create a new
file called Calculator.py.
So to do that recall, I
can type Code down here,
and the name of the file I
want to create, .py, Enter.
That gives me a new tab up top.
So I have already closed Hello.py.
I'm now in Calculator.py.
And let's just make a simple calculator
that does some addition for me.
But I'm going to do it in a file
so that we can iterate on this
and make changes for better
or for worse over time.
Let me go ahead and first
declare a couple of variables.
I'm going to do the mathematical
thing of calling my first variable x,
my second variable y, and
then I'm going to give myself
a third variable z = x + y.
And then I'm going to go
ahead and print out z.
Now this program, admittedly not
very exciting or interesting,
in fact, it's a little less interesting
than printing stuff on the screen
like before with strings,
but we'll build on this
and see what other features exist
in Python that we can leverage.
So hopefully, if Python knows
it's math as well as I do,
when I run Python of Calculator.py,
I should see hopefully that 1 + 2
= indeed 3.
All right, so not that surprising
and not that interesting.
And honestly this isn't
the most useful program
because it's always going
to calculate 1 + 2 = 3.
Let's at least make this program,
say, a little more interactive, right?
We already know from previous examples
how we can get input from the user.
Let's bring back that input function.
And let's do this, let me go ahead
now and at the top of my code,
let's change x to not
be the number 1 always,
let's change it to be
whatever the return
value is of asking the user for x.
And I can use any English or
human language I want here.
I'm going to say, what's x?
Just like I asked
before, what's your name?
And I'm going to do
the same thing for y.
I'm going to use Input again, but
this time change the question to be,
what's y?
All right, at this point, I think I'm
going to leave the rest of the code
the same.
Z = x + y And then
print z but what's nice
now is that I think I have a
nice interactive calculator.
Right, now it's not going
to do 1 + 2 all the time.
It's going to do whatever the user
types + whatever the user types.
So let's try this.
Let me go ahead and run that program.
All right, let's do it.
1 is going to be x, 2 is going to be y,
and of course, everyone in agreement, 1
+ 2 = thr--
huh.
What's going on there?
Either your math class misled
you or I have misled you.
Why don't we call on
someone here to see if you
can't help us reason through what
the bug is, what's the mistake?
Anjali, if I'm saying it right.
AUDIENCE: I think the issue is that
it's concatenating strings because you
use the + operator instead of adding.
DAVID MALAN: Perfect.
So perfect intuition.
We've seen that + is used a little
differently in the context of strings
because it concatenates, that
is, it joins the two strings,
and that seems to Indeed
be what's happening here,
even though the user typed a number.
But the interesting
thing here is that, when
you get user input, because they're
using a keyboard on their Mac
or PC or their phone, it
is always going to be text.
It might look like a
number, but by default,
it's coming from the
keyboard as a string--
that is, as text.
And so, how do we go about
resolving this if ultimately we
don't want to treat
those inputs as strings,
we want to treat them as actual numbers?
Well we need another function
and it turns out in Python
that you can convert sometimes from one
type of data to another type of data,
for instance, from string to INT
by doing something like this.
Let me go back into my
code and let me change
x before adding it to y to be
whatever the integer version of x
is, + whatever the
integer version of y is.
So it turns out that INT is not
only a type of data in Python,
it's also a function,
and it's a function
that if you pass in an
input, like a string,
so long as that string looks
like a number like 1 or like 2,
it will convert it to an actual number
that you can perform mathematics
on instead.
So if I now go back to my
terminal window and run Python--
and let me show you another trick.
"Calculator" is kind of a long word.
It's a little tedious to type.
Notice what I can do in my
terminal window, in a command line
interface in general.
If I start typing C-A-L for
calculator, I can actually
hit Tab to finish my thought.
So auto-complete is possible
in a terminal window like this.
Type the first letter or few
letters and then, boom, with Tab,
it'll finish your thought for you.
Or you can go back in your history
like I did with the Up and Down Arrows.
Let me go ahead and execute this.
What's x?
1.
2.
And there we go.
Now we have a general purpose
calculator that's going to support
not just the addition of
1 and 2, but now any two
integers that the user types.
And let me now improve this, right?
We've seen how we can
make improvements to code
and I don't know if it's going
to necessarily be better,
but let's try this.
Do I really need the z variable?
It's worth noting that I'm
creating a variable called z,
and then I'm immediately using
it on the next line of code.
Now that's not that compelling,
because if you're creating a variable
and then immediately using
it, but never again using it,
did you really need to take the
time to introduce another symbol
and another variable just to
use it once and only once?
Well, maybe not.
Maybe we don't really
need z in this way.
Maybe I should go and
do something like this.
Maybe I should get rid of z here.
Maybe I should change this
to be INT up here, change
this to be INT up here, doing something
that's pretty interesting now.
Even though it's a bit of
new syntax, notice that you
can nest functions, so to speak.
You can put one function call
that is the use of a function
inside of the use of another
function so that the return
value of the inner function
becomes the argument to
or the input to the outer function.
Just like in math, if you have
parentheses, parentheses, parentheses,
your teacher probably
taught you to focus
on what's inside the
innermost parentheses first
and then work your way out.
Same thing with programming.
That's what's Python is going to do.
It's going to look at what's
inside of the parentheses first,
it's going to get the
answer, and then it's
going to pass the return value
to the outermost function.
So what happens on line 1 now is that
the input function gets called first,
then the result of
that, quote unquote one
becomes the input to the INT
function, and same on line 2.
The output of what's y becomes
the input to this INT function.
And now there is no z.
I could just do print x + y.
And because I've taken the time
to convert each of those strings
to an integer, I think we're OK.
So let me try this, Python
of Calculator.py, Enter.
1 and 2, and we're still getting 3.
Not 12, or not 12, 1,2,
we're indeed getting 3.
And we've additionally
gotten rid of the variable
because we didn't necessarily
need it, it seems,
especially if only using it once.
Well here too, let me put everyone's
hands down for just a moment
and let me ask as before--
this version now which uses INT
around the invocations of input,
and does not use z, is this
better than the previous version?
If you want to vote Yes, go ahead.
Or if you prefer the old way, vote No.
The old way, I'll undo all of this
as we vote, instead looked like this.
All right, and let me go back
to now the newest version.
Let's take a hand of
the Yeses, someone who
thinks this latest version is better.
AUDIENCE: I think this way is better
because it allows us to immediately see
what the x and y variables
are with integers
and so we know what to expect from them.
And also the print
argument is more intuitive.
We avoid too much clutter in the code.
DAVID MALAN: I think those
are all good reasons.
It's nice and succinct.
The lines of code are not very long.
I don't need to know what z
is because it doesn't exist.
It just sees print x + y.
I like that.
But someone who prefers the
older way where we did have z
and we more explicitly passed individual
variables to the INT function.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, hi.
I think that the earlier
version is better because when--
I mean, if user input
something else other than,
let's say, I mean, let's
say, they type 1 and 2, like,
so it will be easier to debug.
DAVID MALAN: This version or-- this
version here or the old version?
AUDIENCE: The old version.
DAVID MALAN: OK, that's fair.
And in fact, I'm being very careful
today, as best I can, not to mess up.
I have thus far only inputted
integers when I'm expecting integers.
And Raoul's actually
pointing to something
we'll come back to in the coming weeks,
how do we actually handle errors?
What if the user doesn't type in the
number 1 or the number 2, or a number
at all?
What if they type in a
word like cat, C-A-T?
That's not a number, and I bet I
can't convert it to an integer.
But for today, I'm not
going to focus on that.
I'm just going to hope
that the user cooperates.
But that's not going to be the case.
And so perhaps one way would
set us up for more success
when it comes to handling those errors.
Now for today's purposes,
which is better?
Eh, I mean, I like both.
And I think both of you made very
valid arguments in there too,
so long as you have a justification
that feels pretty reasonable.
I mean, that's what ultimately matters.
But acquiring, again, a
sense of the trade-offs here.
Well, is this way better?
If so, why or why not?
Just understanding what
those trade-offs are.
But generally speaking, prioritizing
readability is a very good thing.
Making your code readable for
someone else is a very good thing
and very good for you too so that
when you wake up the next morning,
or you come back the next
week, or the next year,
you too can read your own
code without having to waste
time trying to remember what you did.
And simplicity tends to be a good
thing too-- keeping your code simple.
So as you get more
comfortable with programming,
you might be tempted to try to combine
an entire program into one long line.
For instance, let me do just that.
Technically speaking, we don't
really need x in a variable.
We don't really need y in a variable.
We could also do this--
I could just get rid
of x and y altogether.
I could then now eliminate that
and make it just one line of code.
OK, so on some sense, you might
be inclined to think, wow,
that's really nice.
You made it one simple line of code.
I would argue this
actually isn't that simple.
Now I think I'm starting
to nest too many things.
I have to think about
print and INT and input.
I then have to notice that, OK,
I've opened two parentheses,
I've closed two of them.
There's a +.
You're making me think too much
and any time you make me think,
you're wasting time.
And any time you complicate
the look of the code like this,
you're just going to increase
the probability of mistakes
and tactical mistakes or
logical errors in your code.
So if all the things we've done, this
is the only one that I would argue,
yes, it's one line and
it's nice and compact.
It's just not readable enough.
I would shy away from doing this,
especially since two of those function
calls are getting input from the user.
But there too, reasonable
people might disagree,
but that's the kind of visceral
reaction you should have sometimes when
code starts getting a little too
complicated, a little too clever,
perhaps, for its own good.
All right, well it's not just
integers we have access to.
Let me propose that we transition from
integers to one more data type here,
namely a float.
So again, a string is
a sequence of text.
An INT is an integer
like negative 1, 0 and 1.
A float is a number with a decimal
point, properly called a floating point
value.
And you can think of the
floating point as being
the decimal that might be over here or
over here with some number of digits
to the left or the right.
Mathematically, it's a real number, a
number that has a decimal point in it.
So that's a third type of
data that Python supports.
Right now our calculator
is somewhat naively
assuming that the user is only
going to type in integers,
but if I want to support
floating point values too,
I think I can just make
a couple of tweaks.
So I'm going to go back to VS Code here.
And instead of just converting
the user's input x and y to
integers on line 1 and 2, let's
just make a simple change.
Let's actually convert it
to a float on the first line
and a float on the second line here.
Now I think, if I go down to my terminal
window and run Python of Calculator.py,
let's type in a number like
1.2 with a decimal point
and 3.4 with a decimal
point, and there we go.
We have 4.6 as the final answer.
So that wouldn't have worked before
if I was only expecting integers
from the user, but now that I'm
expecting floating point values
and accommodating it, I can actually now
do floating point arithmetic as well.
But suppose that I don't
really want the final answer
to be a floating point value like 4.6.
I would be happy if we just
round to the nearest integer.
So I want to support the
user typing in floating point
values with decimal points,
but at the end of the day,
I just want to round the result to the
nearest possible integer, for instance.
Well it turns out that here too Python
comes with some functionality built in.
And in fact, if we return
to this URL from earlier
wherein all of the Python
built-in functions are listed,
there's one called
"round" which does exactly
as we would expect, it
takes as input a number
and then rounds it for us, for
instance, to the nearest integer.
But if we look a little closer at
that documentation as we can here--
I'll provide an excerpt--
this is what the function looks
like in the documentation.
And recall that earlier we looked
at the documentation for print
and this is similar in spirit
that this shows us not just
the name of the function but its
available parameters, that is,
inputs that we can provide
when using this function.
But this is a little cryptic
too, just like Print was,
and it adds some syntax.
So let's see.
The name of this function
here is of course Round
and its first argument is a number.
Notice this time there's no
star, there's no star objects
like there was for print.
The Round function takes just one
number as its first argument, period.
That's its positional parameter.
But notice this syntax.
And this is a convention in
programming or technology
more generally, generally speaking,
when you see square brackets
and documentation like
this, this means that you're
about to see something optional.
And so what this means
is that if you want
to specify more precisely the number of
digits that you want the round function
to round to, you can specify it here
by adding a comma and then that number.
So if we read the documentation, if
you don't specify a number of digits,
you just specify the number to round,
it rounds to the nearest integer.
But suppose you want around to the
tenths place, or the hundredths place
that is one or two digits
after the decimal point,
you could additionally pass in comma
1 or comma 2 to be more precise.
So that's what the
documentation, there is saying.
Let's see if we can't then translate
this to some actual code for us.
So if I go back now to
VS Code and I consider
that I want to go ahead and round x and
y, I can do this in a couple of ways.
I could do round x +
y, but you know, I'd
actually kind of prefer to break
this now out into two lines.
I don't have to, and reasonable
people here might disagree,
but I'd like to revert to a
scenario where I'm printing z,
so that I can just a little more
clearly to myself, to others,
say z = the rounded result of x + y.
It's not necessarily
the better way to do it,
but I'm a little more comfortable with
breaking out my thoughts one at a time,
especially if I want to start
commenting each of these chunks of code.
All right, let me go down
to my terminal window
now and run Python of Calculator.py.
What's x?
Let's do 1.2 again.
Then let's do 3.4.
And now it was previously
4.6, but now it's
been rounded up to the nearest integer,
which of course is going to be 5.
All right, what if I wanted to
change this a little further?
What if I wanted to support
maybe really big numbers,
big numbers, irrespective of rounding,
let's just do something like this.
Let me go ahead and run
Python of Calculator.py
again and let me just add 999 + 1.
And notice, I don't have
to type decimal points,
even though I'm converting
to float, my program
will just allow me to type decimal
points, but I don't need to oblige.
The answer of course here should
be, and is in fact, 1,000,
whether or not we round.
So that's just arithmetic
with integers here.
But in the US, we tend to format
long numbers by putting commas
after or before every triple of digits.
Other countries flip it and they
use periods and commas instead.
That's a system setting.
You can change that
on your own Mac or PC
or device for Python or any
language, but for me, I'm
using the US approach here, which
is periods for decimal points
and commas for separators.
What if I wanted this to
be outputted as 1,000?
Just to make it a little more clear that
it's 1,000 and not something like 100.
That's even more useful
when it's like one million--
1,000,000.
Wouldn't it be nice if
we could automatically
output those numbers as well?
Well, it turns out that we can.
There is a way using Python
to actually specify that we
want to include commas like this.
And here we have an opportunity to
bring back our old friend, the F string.
First, let me do something
that's not that productive.
First let me do this.
Let me print out the value
of z, but wait a minute.
I can't just say "z" because
that's literally going to print z
on the screen.
So let me wrap it with those
curly braces like I did before,
but that too was not enough.
I literally needed to add an F
at the beginning of my string
to tell Python that this is
an F string, a format string.
That now is going to print out, not
very interestingly, just the value of z
itself.
So I'm going to great lengths just to
print z when really I could have just
passed z as the sole argument.
But just to ensure that I haven't
broken it, let's do this again.
999 + 1, Enter.
OK, it's still 1,000.
So I didn't make anything worse.
But notice-- and this syntax is
unfortunately a bit cryptic--
notice that I can actually do this.
I can put a colon after the z
and I can put a comma thereafter.
This looks very cryptic,
admittedly, and even I
have to constantly look things
like this up in the documentation
to remember the syntax.
But here, let me run it again.
Python of Calculator.py,
999 1 and now notice
that the number has been
automatically formatted for me.
If I were in a different
country or locale,
I could absolutely override this to
use periods instead of commas or vise
versa.
But in this case here, it's just
happening for me automatically.
So there too we see a hint of what
it means to really format a string.
There's even more power--
more powerful capabilities
built into that.
All right, let me pause
here to see if there's
any questions now on floats, on
rounding, or on this use of F strings.
AUDIENCE: Yes, so I have a question.
So when using floats,
is there like a cap
to how many decimal points it can have?
DAVID MALAN: A really good question.
So floats, yes, and this is a
problem we'll revisit before long.
Floats cannot represent
numbers infinitely precisely.
In a nutshell, because computers
only have so much memory.
They only have a finite
amount of memory.
You and I only have a finite amount
of hardware inside of the computer,
so at some point, they're
going to have to round.
Right now I'm rounding automatically.
Effectively computers will
eventually have to do that for us,
but we'll see that as a
fundamental problem before long.
Allow me to turn back just for
a few final examples on float
before we introduce a few final
examples that allow us not just
to use functions, but to make our own.
Let me propose that we also try our
hands at a bit of division here.
Let me propose that we
modify this calculator now
to still take a couple of
floats, but let's now just do
something a little simpler than--
a little different from this,
just doing x divided by y.
And let me go ahead and
get rid of my format string
and just keep it simple for
now, printing out z instead.
And what are we going to see here?
Well just some simple division.
So Python of Calculator.py, let's
do something like 2 divided by 3,
and of course I get 0.66666.
And to Ethan's question a moment
ago, it does seem to be finite.
It's not rounding in a weird way here,
but I only seem to see so many digits.
That's an inevitability of
using a float in this way.
By contrast, just so you know,
integers nowadays in Python
can be as big as you want them to be.
Unlike other languages,
there is no upper bound
on how big an INT can be
now in Python, but there
is a bound on just how precise
a floating point value can be.
All right, now that I've got some
simple division working here,
let's go ahead and round this.
It would be nice to round this really
long number 0.6666666 and so forth
to maybe just two decimal places.
We've seen how to do this with round,
though, at least in its documentation.
Let's just round this
not to the nearest INT,
by passing in just x divided by y,
which is one argument, once the math is
done inside of the parentheses, I don't
want to pass in just one argument.
I want to pass in two so
that I can specify n digits,
number of digits, which you'll recall
was the second parameter for round.
Let me go ahead and run
Python of Calculator.py.
I'll do the same thing--
2 and then 3, 0.67.
So here too we see a way of rounding
now, not just to a nearest integer,
but to a nearest number of digits.
But there's another way to do this here.
And in fact, this evokes
our F string example again.
Let me go ahead and change this.
Suppose that you didn't remember the
round function or, for some reason,
you didn't want to use it.
You instead want to just
use a format string.
Well, let's go there.
Let me do "z" but let me surround
it with those curly braces.
Let me add the F at the beginning, and
again, this is not interesting yet.
This is just going to print out z,
but I'm adding a lot more complexity
to turn it into an F string.
But notice I can do something else
after my variable name, after the colon.
If this were going to
be a big integer, I
might want to use a comma like before
to separate each triple of numbers
with commas.
But I don't.
I'm going to use a different
sequence of characters.
I'm going to say 0.2F and this too is
one of these very cryptic things I have
to constantly look up because I
forget if I don't use it that often.
So don't be intimidated if this
looks especially weird, but this is,
according to the
documentation, the way you
specify using an F string how
many digits you want to print.
So let me run this
version of the calculator.
Type in 2 and then 3, we
get the exact same thing.
But again, this is just
consistent with my claim
that in programming we can so
very often solve the same problem
in multiple ways.
This is just now the F string
approach to that very same problem.
All right, which one is better?
It depends.
In this case, they're pretty equivalent.
You can imagine, though, it being
useful to use a function sometimes
so that you can pass in an argument
like n digits as that second argument,
or you can imagine just deciding
in advance that you want 0.2
and then writing it like this.
Let's transition now from focusing
on strings and on integers and on
floats to focusing now
on functions themselves.
We began today by
focusing on how you can
use functions that come with Python.
But wouldn't it be nice if you
could invent your own functions,
especially if, to our
point earlier, you find
yourself solving the same kind
of problem again and again?
It's nice that Python comes
with the print function
because it's really useful to be
able to print things on the screen,
but wouldn't it be nice if you could
print specific things on the screen
by just calling your own function?
Well let me propose that we do this.
Let me go back to VS Code here and let
me propose that we go back to Hello.py.
I'm going to reopen Hello.py
where we left it before
and I'm going to go
ahead now and propose
that we consider how we can start
improving this further by making
our own function.
I have written so many programs
today that just say Hello
and each time I'm using print.
But wouldn't it have been nice
if, from the beginning of today,
we could just call a function called
Hello that just says Hello for us?
Now the authors of
Python years ago didn't
think that we need a special
function just to say Hello,
but I would like that to exist.
I'm saying Hello so
many times, I just want
to be able to call a function Hello.
So I'm going to start from scratch here.
I'm going to delete all
of my code from earlier
and I'm going to pretend for the moment
that a function called Hello exists.
And I'm going to do
just as I did before.
I'm going to get the user's
name with the input function,
asking what's your name, question mark.
And now I'm going to
call a function Hello
and then I'm going to
print out the user's name.
Now I will admit, Hello doesn't exist,
so bad things are about to happen,
but let's see what.
Let me go down to my terminal window.
Let me run Python of Hello.py.
I think the first line is going to
be OK because that worked before.
And indeed, it's
prompting me for my name.
So let me type in David.
The second line of code
is apparently calling
a function that looks like it's called
Hello, because why is it a function?
It has a parenthesis and a closed
parenthesis immediately after it.
And that's what every function
we've used has looked like.
But Python is not going
to recognize this one.
When I hit Enter now,
I get a name error.
Name "Hello" is not
defined, did you mean Help?
I didn't, although it's opportune that's
what I need at this point is some help,
but I am encountering
this error because why?
The function just doesn't exist.
So how do I make this function exist?
Well I need to create it myself using
this key word, DEF, DEF for define.
So here too, just as STR is short for
string and INT is short for integer,
DEF is short for define.
If and when you want to define,
create, invent your own functions,
you can do so using now
this keyword in Python.
So let me go back to my code here and
let me propose that we define this
perhaps in this way.
At the very top of my file,
I'm going to first take
a moment to define a
function called Hello
using DEF Hello, open parenthesis,
close parenthesis, colon.
What this means now is that Python
is going to treat every line of code
that I indent underneath this one as
the meaning of this new function, Hello.
So DEF is important as is the space.
I get to choose the name of the function
and I'm choosing to call it Hello.
The parentheses with nothing inside
means that this function at the moment
is not going to take any
inputs, no arguments there too.
The colon means, stay
tuned for some indentation.
Everything that's indented
beneath this line of code
is going to be part of this function.
It's going to be a super short
function-- one line of code--
it's just going to print out "Hello."
But now on lines 1 and 2, I have
invented my own function Hello.
Notice these dots that have
now magically appeared here.
This is just a setting
of my text editor,
VS Code in this case, that's just
making super explicit to me that I've
hit the space bar four times, or
equivalently the Tab key once,
which is converted
automatically to four spaces.
Generally speaking, I'm going to need to
make sure that all of my indented code
lines up now so that Python knows
that it's all part of the same thing.
But it's easy in this case
because it's just a single line.
But now, thanks to lines 1
and 2, the function Hello
will absolutely exist when
I'm ready to use it on line 6.
So let me go down to my terminal window
and run Python of Hello.py, Enter.
Here comes my name again.
And now when I hit Enter,
I now see Hello, David.
All right, we've kind of
regressed though, right?
This is not nearly as
pretty as it once was.
I think we can probably do better
than this by improving things further.
Why don't we consider,
though, how we might
say parameterize this same function?
That is to say, can we customize Hello
to maybe take the user's name as input
so that we can say, not only Hello, but
the person's name all on one line, all
in one breath?
Well I think we can do this.
Let me propose that
we do this as follows.
Let me go ahead and up in my code,
let me inside of these parentheses,
let me come up with
my own parameter name.
I have complete choice
here and I'm going
to say that the name of my
parameter will be the word To.
Why?
Because I want my function to
sound like the verb it represents--
Hello.
But who do you want to say Hello to?
Well I'm going to call my
parameter for this function
To, just because in English,
it kind of sounds nice to me.
Hello To, who do you
want to say Hello to?
That's why I'm calling this
parameter To instead of something
simpler like x or y or z.
All right, well what do I
want to do with the word To?
Well I can do a couple
of different things.
We've seen like so many different
ways to implement Hello.
Let me just add a comma
there for grammar's sake.
And then let me put the word To
after that as the second argument
to the function Hello.
There's other ways we can do
this and we've seen so many,
but this one looks a little
clear to me, I'll say.
What's going to happen next?
Well I don't think I need
this extra print line here.
I think what I'm going to do is
this, I'm going to go ahead here
and print out not the person's name
manually, I'm going to instead say,
Hello parentheses name.
So what am I now doing?
On lines 1 and 2 I'm defining my
very own function called Hello,
but this time that
function has been designed
to take a parameter, a
single parameter, as input.
And I'm using the value
of that parameter which
I called To to plug into
print so that I see not only
Hello but also that person's name.
What am I doing on line 5?
Same as always, I'm just
getting the user's name.
Line 6, I'm not only
calling Hello, I'm passing
as input the name
variable as an argument
so that that's what
gets passed into Hello.
And what's happening here
is essentially this--
even though the variable is called
Name here, when the function
itself is called, the computer assumes
that same value is now called To.
So Name is essentially copied
to another variable called
To so that in the context of Hello, I
can say Hello to that variable instead.
And we'll see in a moment what happens
if we don't keep those straight.
Let me go ahead and run
Python of Hello.py, Enter.
What's your name?
And now I'm crossing my fingers.
Enter.
There we go.
We're back in business, but now I have
my own custom function called Hello
that's allowing me to say
Hello to a specific person.
And here's where now things
can get really fancy.
What if you wanted your Hello function
to say Hello to someone specific,
but, you know what, if you don't
know who you want to say Hello to,
you want to say Hello
to the whole world,
you can give parameters default values.
We've seen that.
Recall that with print there
was a default value for SEP,
for the separator.
There was a default value
for END, the line ending.
We can do that too,
and here's the syntax.
If you want the value of
this parameter by default,
if not provided by the programmer,
to be equal to "world,"
you literally do that in the same
line you're defining the function.
And I'll admit, it's starting
to look more cryptic,
but I'm still just defining
a function called Hello, it
takes a parameter called
To, but I'm assigning it
with the equal sign a default value of
"world," just in case the programmer
doesn't call Hello with an argument.
And we can see this here.
Let me change my code to
use Hello in two ways.
On line 5, I'm going to very
simply call Hello, no arguments.
Then on line 6, I'm
going to get the name.
Line 7, I'm going to call
Hello with an argument.
So you'll see Hello now
being used in two ways.
Let me go ahead and
run Python of Hello.py.
I'll type in my name.
Oh, interesting.
Notice I already see
Hello, world, but that's
expected because line 5 happens before
line 6, but once I type my name,
now the program is going to be a
little more polite and say hello to me
personally.
So there too, we see with
relatively simple but new syntax
how you can implement functionality
very similar in spirit to what the print
function gave us automatically.
Now you have control
over doing that yourself.
But let me now make this point too.
One of the whole points of
defining your own functions
is one, just to avoid having to
repeat yourself again and again.
You don't have to actually
keep reinventing the wheel
and keep using the print function
again, and again, and again,
if you just want to say Hello.
Wouldn't it be nice now
if I could move this code
that I wrote for defining the Hello
function, and just to be dramatic,
I'm going to hit Enter a whole
lot of times, 50 lines down,
and put my definition of Hello
way further down in this file.
Why?
Well, just for in the spirit
of out of sight, out of mind,
because if I now rewind to
the start of my program, now
you can take for granted
that, oh, Hello is a function.
Why?
Because it's there on line 1 and it
has an open parenthesis and a closed
parenthesis, which, up until now
has meant, call this function.
And then on line 2 we're
getting a variable from the user
by typing in their name and then we're
calling Hello, passing in that value.
Well at this point, I can just
take for granted that Hello exists,
even if it's way down further in the
file or, as we'll see in future weeks,
even if it's in a
different file altogether.
But there's a problem here.
And let me go ahead and run
this version of Hello.py.
Notice that as soon as I run the
interpreter, Python of Hello.py,
I see a name error, name
Hello is not defined.
Again, did you mean Help?
Well, again, fitting.
I do need some help here, but I
didn't mean to call the function Help.
The problem here, though, is that
Python is just taking me literally.
I have defined my function
Hello all the way down here,
but I'm trying to use it way up here.
And that's not allowed.
Python's interpreter is
going to take you literally
and if you use a
function, it must already
exist by the time you are calling it.
So how do I fix this?
Well, apparently I can't do that.
I have to define any functions I
want at the very top of my file,
but that too could get
me into a bit of trouble
eventually because if I constantly have
to define a function above where I want
to use it, you're kind of
writing code in reverse,
you're constantly writing
functions up here, up here,
up here, as opposed to writing
your code logically, top to bottom.
So let me fix this in a more
standard way, which is to do this.
Generally speaking, you do want
to put the main part of your code
at the top of your file.
And in fact, I'm going to go so far
as to define my function, called Main.
It's not a requirement, but
it's in data convention,
and this just connotes
to the reader that this
is the main part of my program.
I'm going to get rid of my empty Hello
call now and only pass in one version
with Hello, name.
And then down here, a couple
of lines further down,
I'll actually define my Hello function.
Unfortunately, now that I've
reordered the functions in this way,
by putting the main part of my code
at the top and Hello at the bottom
so that my logic kind of flows top
to bottom, if I go ahead and run
Python of Hello.py, Enter.
Nothing whatsoever happens.
If I do it again, nothing
whatsoever happens.
Well, why in the world is this?
Well, just because I've
defined a function called
Main and I've defined a
function called Hello,
doesn't mean that I've actually called--
that is used-- either of them.
Yes, I'm using Hello
inside of Main, but no one
is telling Python to
actually use or call Main.
So in order to tidy this up, the
last thing I need to do in this file,
it seems, is actually
call my main function.
And, in fact, by calling my
main function in this way,
it gets me out of trouble because
now I'm defining Main first
but I'm not calling Hello yet.
I'm defining Hello next, but
I'm not calling Hello next.
I only at the very end
of this file call Main
which has the effect of
running this code up here,
running this code down here,
and it allows me therefore
to organize my file
and order my functions in any way I
want, including Main at the very top,
and solving ultimately that problem
of Python not knowing what's going on.
Now it's important to note
that I defined my function
Hello as taking an
argument To and then I
passed into that function
the value of the variable
that I wanted to say Hello to,
that is the variable called Name.
Because suppose I had done
something a little bit differently.
Suppose that I hadn't defined
Hello is taking an argument,
so I just remove mention of To
and its default value "world."
And I go back up to my
main function and I just
call Hello itself without
passing in any arguments.
And now let me go ahead and
make my one more change,
one more mistake
technically, let me go ahead
and just try to naively print out the
value of Name in the Hello function.
So now to be clear, in my
main function on line 2,
I'm defining my variable called Name
and assigning it the return value
of the input function from the user.
I'm then just calling Hello.
In my Hello function, which now
no longer takes any arguments,
I am calling print,
passing in Hello comma,
and then immediately passing
in Name, the variable
into which I got the user's input.
But the catch is that name
exists now only in Main.
And so watch what happens when I try
to run this version of the program
with Python Hello.py.
I hit Enter.
I'm prompted for my
name, D-A-V-I-D, Enter.
And, argh!
A name error.
Name "Name" is not defined.
So it turns out that this is actually
an issue of what's called scope.
Scope refers to a variable only existing
in the context in which you defined it.
So insofar as I define this
variable, Name in my main function,
I can only use that variable
in my name function.
I can't use it as I've tried
to here in my Hello function.
It doesn't exist in
that so-called scope.
And so this is why now, if I rewind
and undo all of those changes,
you'll see that I'm deliberately
passing Main from my main function
into my Hello function.
And now in the Hello function, it
technically has a different name.
It's called To in that
context, but that's fine.
It's completely up to each individual
function to name its own variables
or name its own arguments,
but this is a way now
that I'm handing to the Hello
function the value of that variable
so it can be printed by Hello as well.
And there's one final
flourish we can add here.
Now that we've implemented Hello,
you'll notice that Hello only
has a so-called side effect.
It only prints out
something to the screen.
Well, what if I also want my function
to not have a side effect, per se,
but actually hand me back a value?
Recall that the input
function returns a value,
the string that the user typed in.
Recall that the INT
function returns a value.
The float function returns a
value that was passed into it.
Well you can use one final
keyword here, literally
Return to return a value
explicitly yourself.
In fact, let me go back
to VS Code here, and I
think we'll return our
attention to Calculator.py
and see if we can't implement one other
version of Calculator.py that actually
has our own function that
even returns a value.
So I'm going to go ahead
and open up calculator/py
and I think this time I'm going to
throw everything away as before,
and I'm just going to start
practicing what we're preaching here.
Define a function called
Main which is now going
to be the main part of my function.
Let's go ahead and now
declare a variable called x,
and assign it to the converted version
of the user's input after asking them,
what's x?
So again, a line of code
quite like we've done before.
And suppose now that what I
want to do is square this value.
I want to take the number
that the user has typed in
and raise it to the power of 2.
So 2 squared would be 4.
3 squared would be 9.
4 squared would be 16, and so forth.
Well how do I go about
implementing a function literally
called Square which actually
doesn't come with Python built-in?
Well, let me assume for the
moment that it does exist, and let
me say something like this--
let me go ahead and
say that printing, how
about x squared is comma square of x.
So what have I done?
I've defined a function called Main
and I've implemented two lines.
The first of these lines
prompts the user for a value
x and converts it to an INT and
stores it in a variable called x.
On line 3, I then say
x squared is and then
I pass a second argument to the
print function, whatever the return
value is of a square function.
But squared doesn't exist
and I'll show you this here,
if I now call Main at the bottom
and I run Python of Calculator.py,
I'll see that x is 2 and then I see a
whole bunch of errors, a name error,
name Square is not defined.
So this isn't a typo here, it's
just the function doesn't exist.
But I think I can make it exist here.
Let me go ahead and define
another function called Square.
This one's going to
take in a number and I'm
going to call it generically
n, as many a programmer would,
just to represent any old number.
And then what do I want to
do in order to square n?
Well a number squared is really
just itself times itself,
so I'm going to do this--
n times n.
But it's not enough just to do
the math yourself, n times n.
You're going to have to return
the actual value n times n
and that's our new keyword here.
When I now do this, watch what happens.
Python of Calculator.py, Enter.
X say shall be 2, x squared is 4.
Let me go ahead now and say x is now 3.
X squared is now 9.
So I've implemented my very own function
that returns the square of a value
and because I'm using
the return keyword, that
ensures that I can pass the
return value of this, just
like the return value of input or
INT or float, to another function,
like print instead.
And here too there's going to be so
many ways to solve this same problem.
I can actually raise
n to the power of 2.
We've not seen this
syntax before, but if you
use two asterisks like this, two stars,
that raises the thing on the left
to the power on the right.
Or it turns out there is
in Python a function called
POW for raising something
to the power that
takes two arguments, the first of which
is the number, the second of which
is the exponent.
So there too, there's just so many ways
to actually solve that same problem
as well.
So ultimately, what have we done here?
We first introduced functions--
these actions or verbs, many of which
come built into Python that you
can just use in your own code.
We then introduced variables via which
you could store those return values
and then maybe do
something more with it.
At the end of the day too.
You now have the ability to create,
to invent your own functions
to solve simple problems
like Hello, or in the weeks
to come-- much more sophisticated, more
challenging, more fun problems as well.